A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Paris, RG 6, SG 1 FA395
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, field offices, Paris, RG 6, SG 1
1935-1976, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller Foundation. Paris (France)
FA395
53.08 Cubic Feet
File Plan note
RG 6.1.
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Biographical/Historical note
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
Scope and Contents note
The International Health Board of the Rockefeller Foundation maintained an office in Paris from 1917 as the headquarters for the work of the Commission for the Prevention of Tuberculosis in France. In 1922, anticipating the transfer of the tuberculosis work to the French, and the expansion of work in Europe, the Board agreed to share space and administrative expenses with the Rockefeller Foundation's Division of Medical Education. The Nursing Survey of the IHB was to be carried on from the same location. Other administrative units of the Foundation concerned with work in Europe used the same office.
The Paris office can be described as a colony of more or less independent units, occupying the same office space, loosely bound together under a chairman and a committee, both advisory in function, and sharing common services. The chairman of the Paris office exercised a general oversight, acting as advisor and coordinator. He was the representative of the President in Paris in the sense that he transmitted all general instruction from the central executives to the group while in the other direction he was spokesman for the group to New York. He had full Power of Attorney for all Rockefeller Foundation property in France. All bank accounts were in his name. He called together and presided over the Paris officers in committees for discussions of mutual problems and in consultation with them either agreed to or rejected their various fellowships and grants-in-aid dockets, his signature being required, as well as that of the Comptroller and divisional representative concerned, on all Paris office grants. Chairmen of the Paris office before World War II were Selskar M. Gunn, 1922-1932; George K. Strode, 1932-1938; A. J. Warren, 1938-1939; and Selskar M. Gunn, 1939-1940.
The office committee, which corresponded roughly to the staff conference in New York, had no legal status whatever yet acquired with the years a definite function. All officers' actions or grants-in-aid, grants for deposed scholars, and fellowships passed through this committee. Here, questions of general policy were discussed.
Officers in divisions in Paris had an integrity and autonomy unknown in New York, that granted by sheer remoteness from the main office. From fund allocated by directors in New York for expenditure in Europe, officers had the power of independent action without reference to New York, limited however to grants-in-aid and fellowships of not more than one year and $3,000.
The Paris office was the fiscal agent of the New York office with respect to European affairs. The Paris office administered payments under appropriations made by the Trustees in New York for European projects. The Comptroller also administered payments under officers actions in Paris, and acted as fiscal agent for the General Education Board and for the national councils with respect to fellows assigned to Europe for study.
The Administrator of the Paris office was charged with the non-divisional functions of the office, i.e., personnel, office quarters, equipment, central services, travel, purchasing, etc. The budget was made up in two sections, the principal part in francs, the lesser in dollars.
Divisions represented at the Paris office before World War II were the International Health Board, later the International Health Division, the Division of Studies, the Division of Medical Education, the Medical Sciences Division, the Divisions of Natural and social Sciences. Officers assigned to the Paris office included F. Elisabeth Crowell, E. E. Day, Alan Gregg, Selskar M. Gunn, Lauder Jones, Tracey B. Kittredge, Robert A. Lambert, H. M. Miller, Daniel P. O'Brien, Richard M. Pearce, F. F. Russell, George K. Strode, Wilbur E. Tisdale, John Van Sickle, George E. Vincent, A. J. Warren, and Warren Weaver.
In 1941, the Paris office closed for the duration of the war. The space was used for a time by an agency of the Vichy Government under the direction of Dr. Alexis Carrell, and the Foundation's work in Europe was continued by the newly formed Rockefeller Foundation Health Commission. One staff member, the Comptroller, Robert Letort, a native Frenchman, remained on the payroll looking after the Foundation's interests. In 1945 Letort and Charles N. Leach, a member of the RHC, reopened the office. It remained open until 1959, but its functions and character were completely changed. It became a place maintained for the convenience of a small group of officers assigned more or less permanently to Paris and for the convenience also of the somewhat larger group who used Paris as a base for European travel. It still had a chairman with whom the New York office, usually through the vice president, corresponded on questions of general policy. Only two divisions, Medical Sciences and International Health Division, maintained permanent staff. The Paris office postwar had no funds for allocation of grants-in-aid and fellowships. These were administered from New York. Except for payments to French projects, all appropriations to European projects were now paid from New York. The Staff maintained services such as filing and bookkeeping and provided secretarial service. Personnel assigned to the Paris office in the postwar period included Johannes H. Bauer, Elizabeth W. Brackett, Robert P. Burden, John B. Grant, Frederic C. Lane, Charles N. Leach, John Maier, H. M. Miller, Daniel P. O'Brien, Paul Russell, R. Rolf Struthers, Mary E. Tennant. Chairmen of the Paris office were Rolf Struthers, 1946-1954, and John Maier, 1954-1959.
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 20 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The files of the Paris office have been sorted and weeded several times over the years. What remains is far from a complete record. The arrangement, however, is as received; that is, these files were not processed through the New York office but were in storage since shipment from France. The filing system has not been altered.
Related Archival Materials note
Records related to those of the Paris office include minutes of meetings of the Paris office committee which can be found in Record Group 3, Administration, Program and Policy, Series 904 Officers Conferences. Program and policy reports relevant to Paris office administration are 900 Org. 33, 900 Org. 36, 900 Pro. 16. There is also material in Record Group 1.1, Projects, Series 700, European Office Administration, as well as Series 500, France.
Medical sciences; Public health; Agriculture; Agricultural innovations -- Mexico; Agricultural innovations; Medical research -- India; Social sciences -- India; India; Green Revolution; Life sciences; Latin America; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Agriculture -- India; Philanthropy -- United States; Colombia; Charities; Medical research; Medical education; Philanthropy
- Pre-war, 1922-1941; 1; 46 Boxes; 28 cubic feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Programs included are Medical Sciences (MS), Natural Sciences (NS), International Health Division (IHD), Social Sciences (SS). Correspondence is mainly between Europeans, grantees and others, and divisional officers in the Paris office. Subjects are public health, institutes of public health, neurology, physiology, nursing, biology, and psychiatry. Correspondents include Arne Tiselius, Jean Piaget, Hugh Cairns, Alan Gregg, and F. Elizabeth Crowell. There is correspondence in French and German. There is a section designated "General" that includes nondivisional correspondence, and a section for League of Nations correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  Files in three subseries (correspondence, financial material, reports) numbered continuously. Correspondence is arranged by program, within program alphabetically by country, within country alphabetically by title (person, subject, or institution). Strict chronological arrangement is followed within folders; reports and reprints are filed with correspondence unless numbers or dimensions necessitated a second folder. Files may include grants, general correspondence, declinations, or fellowships all in the same folder. That is, all correspondence with a given person or institution is general filed together regardless of its nature.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Related material can be found in the Rockefeller Foundation's Projects files, RG 1.1, under European country numbers, especially 500 France and 700 Europe.
  - Pre-war - Correspondence, 01
    - MS Austria, 1925-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Chargoff, E. - Laboratoire de Recherches sur las Tuberculose - 1933-1934 Handovksy, Hans - Ghent University - Pharmacological Laboratory - 1933-1934 Jarisch, Adolf - Pharmacological Institute - Innsbruck - 1926 Luger, Alfred - Vienna University - Medical Library - 1925-1926 Rosler, Hugo - Vienna Heart Station - 1929
    - MS Austria - Graz University, 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Hausler, Hans - Pharmacological Institute - 1929 Knaus, Herman - Womans Clinic - 1926-1927 Soltys, Armulf - Institute of Medical Chemistry - 1931-1934 Wagner, Richard - Institute of Physiology - 1929
    - MS Austria - Vienna University, 1927-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Buhler, Charlotte/Karl - Institute of Psychology - 1934-1935 Durig, A. - Institute of Physiology - 1926-1935 Eppinger, Hans - Medical Clinic - 1934-1935 Maresch, R. - Institute of Pathological Anatomy - 1927 Schonbauer, L. - Surgical Division
    - MS Belgium, 1923-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Van Bogaert, Ludo - Institut Bynge - Neurological Section - 1936-1937 Heymans, Carl - Ghent University - Institute of Pharmacology - 1934-1936 Medical Literature - 1923, 1926, 1929
    - MS Belgium - Brussels Neurological Center, 1927-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - MS Belgium - Brussels University, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Bremer, F. - Laboratory of General Pathology - 1937-1940 Hopital S. Pierre - 1932-1933
    - MS Bulgaria - Sofia University - Medical Faculty, 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - MS China - China Medical Board, 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Pillat, A. - (Faculty) - 1927-1940 Lim, R. K. S. - "Medical Education in the U.S.S.R. - 1935
    - MS Czechoslovakia, 1924-1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Brno University - Medical Literature - 1924 Florian, Jan - Institute of Histology and Embryology, Brno - 1934-1937 Kimla, Rudolf - Czech Medical Faculty, Prague - 1934-1937 Knaus, Hermann - German Medical Faculty, Prague - 1934-1937
    - MS Czechoslovakia - Czech University, Prague - Faculty of Medicine, 1921-1922, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - MS Czechoslovakia - German University, Prague, 1921-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Breinl, Friedrich - Institute of Hygiene - 1932-1936 Gamper, Edward - Psychological and Neurological Clinic - 1932 Equipment - 1921-1929
    - MS Czechoslovakia - Pelc, Hynek - Institute of Public Health, 1924-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - MS Denmark, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Einarson, Lars - Aarhus University - Anatomical Institute - 1939-1940 Kemp, Tage - "Report of Visits to Various Institutes, Laboratores, etc. for Human Genetics in Europe" - 1934 Orskiv, Soren - Copenhagen University - Medico-Physiological Institute - 1933 Plum, Preben - Copenhagen University - Department of Pediatrics - 1938-1940
    - MS Denmark - Copenhagen University - Institute of General Pathology and Institute of Human Genetics, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - MS Denmark - Copenhagen University, 1924-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Institute of Zoophysiology - Rehberg, Paul - 1924-1935 Neurological Department - Fog, Mogens - 1933-1940 Psychiatric Clinic - 1936-1940
    - MS Denmark - Fischer, Albert - Biological Institute, Copenhagen, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - MS England, 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Burden Neurological Clinic - 1939 Colchester Research in Hereditary Mental Diseases - 1934-1939 Fisher, R. A. - (Serological Genetics) - 1935-1940 Guys Hospital - Department of Nervous Diseases and Psychological Medicine - 1934-1939 Hill, A. V. - University College, London - (Physiology) - 1934-1938 Lister Institute of Preventative Medicine - 1936
    - MS England, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      National Institute of Industrial Psychology - 1930-1932 National Institute for Medical Research - 1932-1934 Queen Charlotte Hospital - (Puerperal Fever Research) - 1931 Royal College of Surgeons of England - (Library) - 1938-1939 - (Sympathetic Nervous System) - 1938-1939 St. Batholomew's Hospital - (Endocrinology) - 1938-1939 Vaughan, Janet - (Pathology) - 1936-1937
    - MS England - Cairns, Hugh - (Neurosurgery), 1928-1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - MS England - Cambridge University, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Department of Medicine - 1937-1938 Department of Pharmacology - 1936-1937 Psychological Laboratory - 1936-1937 School of Biochemistry - 1939
    - MS England - Cambridge University - Psychological Laboratory, 1927-1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - MS England - Harris, Charles F. - (St. Bartholomew's Hospital) - (Pediatrics), 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - MS England - Maudsley Hospital, London - (Miscellaneous Grant Correspondence), 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - MS England - Medical Research Council - (Fellowships), 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - MS England - National Hospital Queen Square - (Nervous Diseases), 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - MS England - Oxford University, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Department of Biochemistry - Peters, R. A. -1934-1939 Department of Human Anatomy - 1934-1939 Department of Pharmacology - Franklin, Kenneth J. - 1932-1939 - Burn, J.H. - 1938-1939
    - MS England - Oxford University - Physiological Laboratory - (Sherrington, Charles B.), 1929-1936 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - MS England, 1928-1940 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Tavistock Clinic - Institute of Medical Psychology - 1938-1940 University College Hospital, London - 1928-1935
    - MS Esthonia - Tartu University - Medical Faculty, 1926-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - MS Finland - Helsingfors University, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Laboratory of Medical Chemistry - Simola, P. E. - 1934-1935 Pharmacology Laboratory - Vartiainen, A. - 1935
    - MS France, 1923-1939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Baruk, Henri - Maison Nationale de Sante - 1929-1938 Developmental Aid - 1931, 1933 Du Nuoy, P. Lecomte - Institut Pasteur - 1929-1936 Emergency Work - 1939 Fellowships - 1923 Leriche, R. - University of Strasbourg - Surgical Clinic - 1932-1938 Lhermitte, Laboratoire de Neurologie de la Fondation Djering - 1933 Messimy, R. - Institut de Neurobiologie, La Salpetriere - 1938 Nancy University - Institute of Hygiene - 1928-1932 Philomatic Society - (Neurophysiology) - 1939
    - MS France - College de France, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Courrier, Robert - (Endocrinology) - 1938-1940 Fessard, A. - (Neurophysiology) - 1937-1940
    - MS France - Lyon University, 1933-1940 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Faculty of Medicine - 1933-1936 Lepine, Jean - (Neurology) - 1937-1940 Nursing School - 1934-1935 Physiological Laboratory - Hermann, H. - 1937-1939
    - MS France - Marseille University, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Cornil, Lucien - Laboratory of Pathological Anatomy - 1937-1939 Mosinger, Michel - Laboratory of Neurobiology - 1938-1940
    - MS France, 1929-1941 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Paris Museum of Natural History - Anthony, Paul R. - 1932-1938 Paris Radium Institute - Biological Laboratory - 1929-1941
    - MS France - Paris University - Faculty of Medicine, 1927-1939 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - MS France - Paris University, 1927-1941 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Bertrand, Ivan - Institute of Neurobiology - 1934-1940 Champy, Ch. - Histological Laboratory - 1934-1940 Clinique de la Tuberculose - 1928-1933 Laboratory of General Physiology - Monnier, A. M. - 1936-1938 Pharmacological Laboratory - Tiffeneau, M. - 1927-1936 Vincent, Clovis - (Neurosurgery) - 1937-1941
    - MS France - Strasbourg University, 1925-1937 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Faculty of Medicine - 1925-1934 Institute of Embryology - 1930-1937 Grabar, Pierre - Institute of Biological Chemistry - 1932 Medical Clinic B. - 1935-1936
    - MS France - Toulouse University - Bugnard, L. C. - (Pharmacodynamics), 1934-1940 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - MS Germany, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      Berlin University - Pathological Institute - Rossle, R. - Doljanski, L. - 1933 Breslau University - Neuropsychiatric Clinic - Lange, Johan - 1933-1939 Breslau Wenzel-Hancke Krankenhaus - Neurological Clinic - Foerster, Otfried - 1930-1936 Frankfurt University - Bluntschli, Hans - Institute of Anatomy - 1931
    - MS Germany - Deposed Scholars, 1932-1940 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Ellinger, Phillip - (Pharmacology) - 1933-1936 Feldberg, Werner - (Physiology) - 1933-1935 Friedmann, Ulrich - (Bacteriology) - 1932-1934 Goldstein, Kurt - (Biology) - 1933-1934 Guttman, Erich - (Psychiatry) - 1934-1940 Hober, Rudolf - (Physiology) - 1932-1934 Katz, Bernard - (Physiology) - 1936-1938 Krayer, Otto - (Parmacology) - 1933-1937 Krebs, H. A. - (Biology) - 1932-1933
    - MS Germany - Deposed Scholars, 1933-1939 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      Laser, Hans - (Parasitology) - 1933-1934 Levin, Ernst - (Neurosurgery) - 1933-1938 Lewinthal, Walter - (Virology) - 1933-1934 Mayer, Edmund - (Biology) - 1933 Mayer-Gross, willy - (Psychiatry) - 1933 Meyer, alfred - (Physiology) - 1933-1935 Plaut, Felix - (Neurosyphilis) - 1939 Prausnitz, Karl - (Public Health) - 1932-1935 Riese, Walther - (Neurology) - 1933-1937 Wertheimer, Ernst - (Physiology) - 1933-1936
    - MS Germany - Freiburg University, 1925-1938 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      Aschoff, Ludwig, Institute of Pathological Anatomy - 1930-1936 Institute of Hygiene - Uhlenhuth, Paul - 1928-1936 Medical Clinic - 1932-1936 Neuropsychiatric Clinic - 1925, 1932-1938
    - MS Germany -, 1931-1940 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Geissen University - Pathological Institute - 1933 Halle University - Physiological Institute - 1931-1935 Hamburg University - Neurological Clinic - 1932-1940
    - MS Germany - Heckscher Institute for Psychiatry, 1935-1939 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - MS Germany, 1926-1935 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Kaiser Wilhelm Institute - 1926-1933 Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Anthropology - Fischer, Eugen - 1933 Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Biology - Warburg, Otto - 1929-1935
    - MS Germany, 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Psychiatry - 1935-1936 Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Psychiatry - 1931-1936
    - MS Germany, 1926-1939 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Leipzig University - Institute of Physiological Chemistry - 1934-1938 Marburg University - Pathological Institute - Verse, Professor - 1926-1928 Munich University - Psychiatric Clinic - 1932-1939
    - MS Germany, 1931-1936 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      Refugees, High Commission for - 1934-1935 Robert Koch Institute for Infectious Diseases - 1932-1936 Robert Koch Institute for Infectious Diseases - Schilling, Claus - (Tropical Disease Study) - 1931-1933
    - MS Germany - Wurzburg University, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      Neurological Clinic - 1935-1938 Physiological Institute - Schriever, Hans - 1934-1938
    - MS Greece - Athens University - Medical Faculty, 1926-1936 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - MS Holland - Amsterdam University, 1928-1939 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      Laboratory of Hygiene and Bacteriology - 1928 Neurological Clinic - 1933-1939 Pharmacological Laboratory - 1932-1938 Physiological Laboratory - 1937-1939
    - MS Holland, 1927-1939 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      Groningen University - Mulder, J. - (Pneumonia Study) - 1938-1939 Herrick, C. Judson - "Report of Brief Visits to the Laboratories of Medicine and Biology in the Netherlands and Belgium" - 1927
    - MS Holland - Leiden University, 1934-1941 (Box 5, Folder 54)